Finding Aid for Clippert Family papers, 1863-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clippert Family papers 1863-1962
Clippert family.
1 oversize folder
2.5 linear feet
2008162 Aa 2; Ac
Clippert family of Detroit, Michigan; family materials include letters and notes of Harrison F. Clippert while serving with the 65th Coast Artillery Corps during World War I; also papers relating to Clippert Brick Company, a family business started by Conrad J. Clippert.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Charles F. Clippert II (donor no. 9212 ) and came to the library in 2008.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Conrad J. Clippert (1834-1901) was the patriarch of the family, and came to the United States from Hesse-Cassell, Germany. He worked under R.H. Hall and learned the business of brick manufacture. He began his own company in 1876, and was eventually elected sheriff of Wayne County in 1880 and 1882. He later served as vice-president of the Central Savings Bank of Detroit, and served as an officer of the institution until his death. His children were George H., Charles F., William, Conrad II, Fred, Hattie, and Julius.
George H. Clippert (1860-1925) worked in the railroad service before taking over the family business, renaming it in 1899 as the George H. Clippert & Bro. Brick Company. He was quite active in Detroit, belonging to several organizations: the Detroit Builders & Traders' Exchange (vice-president and president); Detroit Board of Commerce; Wayne County and Home Savings Bank (board of directors); Board of Control of the State Industrial Home for Girls (chairman); Union Lodge of the Masonic Order; Benevolent and Protective Order of the Elks; Harmonie Society; and the Detroit Athletic Club. His children were Edna (married to Charles Kennedy whose papers are also at the Bentley), Harrison F., Phyllis M., Helen M., and George F.
Charles F. Clippert was a partner with George H. in joining with their father's firm in 1884 when the business became Conrad Clippert & Sons. His children were Conrad J. III, Marie, Hermine A., and Ruth (married to Douglas Roby, whose papers are also at the Bentley).
Harrison F. Clippert was in Engineering at the University of Michigan (class of 1911) though he did not graduate. He served in World War I under the 65th Coast Artillery Corps, spending some time in France.
George F. Clippert attended the University of Michigan during the 1920's (where he was a member of the Delta Tau Delta fraternity), and went to the Junior Plattsburg Military Training Camp at Lake Champlain in 1918.
The Clippert papers are divided into nine series, six of which are organized under individual family members. The other three deal with the Clippert Brick Company and various Miscellanea and Photographs.
Subjects:
Brick trade--Michigan--Detroit.; Clippert Brick Company.; Clippert family.; Delta Tau Delta Fraternity. University of Michigan Chapter.; Detroit (Mich.)--Commerce.; United States. Army. Coast Artillery Regiment, 65th.; University of Michigan--Students.; World War, 1914-1918.
Contributors:
Clippert, Conrad J., 1834-1901.; Clippert, George H.; Clippert, Harry, 1888-1972.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Clippert Brick Company
  The Clippert Brick Company series has documents that are not directly involved with any specific family member, but rather the company in general. It includes financial documents, minutes, and Articles of Association.
  - Finances 1927-1931, 1 expandable folder (Box 1)
  - "The Clippert Brick Company" (a history written by Joseph E. Zias) (Box 1)
  - Lighthouse Digest: article describing how 40-Mile Point Lighthouse purchased its bricks from the Clippert Company (Box 1)
  - General 1921, 1945 (Box 1)
- Conrad J. Clippert
  Conrad J. Clippert series documents the founding of the Clippert Brick Company and has a handful of letters.
  - Brick Company
    - Correspondence 1885-1892 (Box 1)
    - Finances 1871-1887 (Box 1)
    - Legal Documents 1863-1885 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1869-1889 (Box 1)
      (appointment to notary, patent license)
- George H. Clippert
  George H. Clippert's series continues to document the family business and also has some early records of the Detroit Brickmaker's Exchange.
  - Correspondence 1884, 1894, 1900 (Box 1)
  - Brick Company
    - Correspondence 1885-1921 (Box 1)
    - Finances 1884-1908 (Box 1)
    - Bank Books, circa 1892 (Box 1)
    - Legal Documents 1870-1924 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Brickmaker's Exchange 1893-1894 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1889-1893 (Box 1)
    (appointment to notary, business university admittance)
- Charles F. Clippert
  The Charles F. Clippert series has a small amount of correspondence relating to the Clippert Brick Company.
  - Correspondence 1899-1935 (Box 1)
- Harrison F. Clippert
  The Harrison F. Clippert series consists of a large number of letters (written to his future wife Ethelyn Reuss) and military records (manuals, training materials and documents concerning transportation). The library also has in its printed collection the volume edited by Charles F. Clippert entitled World War I correspondence of Harry Clippert (1917 to 1919) (2001).
  - Correspondence
    - 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1918 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1918 (Box 1)
    - 1919 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
  - Military Material
    - Training Manuals 1909-1917, 3 expandable folders (Box 2)
    - Notebooks, 1 expandable folder (Box 2)
    - Homage to Marshal Foch 1921 (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea (Box 2)
      (includes mileage allowance and rolling papers)
  - 65th Artillery, C.A.C (Coast Artillery Corps)
    - Correspondence 1917-1918 (Box 2)
    - Training Material 1917-1918, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Transportation 1918 (Box 2)
    - "The History of the 65th Artillery, CAC 1917-1919" (Box 2)
- George F. Clippert
  George F. Clippert's series has a small amount of correspondence and some material relating to his fraternity- Delta Tau Delta.
  - Correspondence 1921, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Delta Tau Delta (Box 2)
    (includes photographs)
- Conrad J. Clippert III
  A few letters from the 1960's concerning the company are filed under the Conrad J. Clippert III series.
  - 1958-1962 (Box 2)
- Miscellanea
  The Miscellanea series contains a history of the Clippert family, a history of common brick making in Detroit, and some political badges.
  - Political Badges (Box 2)
  - "History of the Clippert Family of Michigan," 1977 by Glenn Lee Wilkins (Box 2)
  - "History of Common Brick Making in Detroit" (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The final series contains several Photographs containing members of the family as part of larger groups, military units or a banquet.
  - "Junior Plattsburg Military Training Camp Summer 1918 Lake Champlain", rolled panoramic photograph (Box 3)
  - "Members of the Junior Plattsburg Camp 1918", rolled panoramic photograph (Box 3)
  - "Battery 'C' 65th Artillery (C.A.C.) REF, Camp Dix, NY February 1919", rolled panoramic photograph (Box 3)
  - "Twenty-Fifth Annual Convention Dinner: National Brick Manufacturers' Association and the Common Brick Manufacturers' Association of America. Hotel Pennsylvania, NY. February 3, 1921", rolled panoramic photograph (Box 3)
  - "Builders and Traders Fourth Annual Outing June 16, 1914" (Box 3)
  - "Locks Panama Canal", rolled panoramic photograph (Box 3)
  - Harrison F. Clippert (Box 3)
    (small portrait in a separate envelope)
  - "Delta Tau Delta 1922" group photograph (Folder 1)
  - "Harry's Engineering Class, UofM 1909 Class of 1911" group photograph (Folder 1)
  - Rotogravure Supplement to the Detroit Free Press, March 10, 1918 containing a short statement of Lt. Harrison F. Clippert (Folder 1)